Guide to the Douglas L. Brutlag Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Douglas L. Brutlag papers
1968-1999
SC0651
Brutlag, Douglas L.
18 Linear feet (19 boxes)
The papers document Brutlag's research and teaching in biochemistry and his work in bioinformatics. The papers include research notebooks, 1972-1982 and undated, some of which were compiled by Denise Lew and Bruce Moseley; class syllabi, exams, problem sets, and Brutlag's notes and lecture outlines, 1968-1980; and papers pertaining to bioinformatics, 1981-1999, which include correspondence, articles, memoranda, proposals, reports, and computer software documents.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
The papers were given to the Stanford University Archives by Douglas L. Brutlag in 2002.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 48 hours in advance of intended use.
Alternative Formats
At one time, scanned copies of most of these documents could be found at http://hrst.mit.edu/hrs/bioinformatics/public/Documents.htm under "Brutlag-Friedland-IntelliGenetics Collection." As of 2009, researchers are directed to contact Tim Lenoir (Lenoir@duke.edu).
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Douglas L. Brutlag earned his B.S. in biology at the California Institute of Technology in 1968, and his Ph.D. in biochemistry at Stanford in 1972. He joined the Stanford faculty in 1974 as an assistant professor of biochemistry, becoming a tenured associate professor in 1980. Brutlag's work bridges the fields of biology and computer sciences, in the rapidly expanding field of bioinformatics. Brutlag is a cofounder of IntelliCorp and IntelliGenetics Inc., served on the Scientific Advisory Board (Chairman) of Time Logic Inc., and is Director of the Bioinformatics Resource at Stanford University.
Description of the Collection
The papers document Brutlag's research and teaching in biochemistry and his work in bioinformatics. The papers include research notebooks, 1972-1982 and undated, some of which were compiled by Denise Lew and Bruce Moseley; class syllabi, exams, problem sets, and Brutlag's notes and lecture outlines, 1968-1980; and papers pertaining to bioinformatics, 1981-1999, which include correspondence, articles, memoranda, proposals, reports, and computer software documents.
Access Terms
Brutlag, Douglas L.; Lew, Denise.; Moseley, Bruce.; Biochemistry--Study and teaching.; Bioinformatics; DNA Replication.; DNA--Biosynthesis.; Molecular biology--Data processing
Collection Contents
- Binder with Research Notes, Books I and II, pp. 1-332 (with index) (Box 1)
- Binder with Research Notes, Books III and IV, pp. 333-667 (with index) (Box 1)
- Binder with Research Notes, Books V and VI, pp. 668-933 (with index) (Box 1)
- Binder with Research Notes, Books VII and VIII, pp. 934-1218 (with index) (Box 1)
- Binder with Research Notes, Books IX and X, pp. 1219-1553 (with index) (Box 2)
- Binder with Research Notes, Books XI and XII, pp. 1554-2077 (with index) (Box 2)
- Binder with Research Notes, I and II, pp. 1-342 (with index) (Box 2)
- Binder with Research Notes, III and IV, pp. 343-670 (with index) (Box 2)
- Binder with Research Notes, V and VI, pp. 671-986 (with index) (Box 3)
- Binder with Research Notes, VII and VIII, pp. 987-1280 (with index) (Box 3)
- Binder with Research Notes, IX and X, pp. 1281-1515 (with index) (Box 3)
- Binder with Research Notes, XI, pp. 1516-end (no index) (Box 3)
- Binder with Research Notes, I and II, pp. 1-155 (with index) (Box 4)
- Unlabelled binder 1972-73, pp. 1-188 and 1-48 (with index) (Box 4)
- Biochemistry 201/102 - problem sets, exams, etc., 1968-1974 (Box 4)
- Research Notebook (with index), 1974 Dec-1975 Dec (Box 5)
- Research Notebook (with index), 1976 Jan-Dec (Box 5)
- Research Notebook (with index), 1977 Feb-Dec (Box 5)
- Research Notebook (with index), 1977 Oct-1978 Aug (Box 5)
- Research Notebook (with index), 1978 Sep-1979 Feb (Box 6)
- Research notebook by Denise Lew, Satellite DNA (with index), 1980-1982 Feb (Box 6)
- Research notebook by Denise Lew, Topoisomerase I (with index), 1980 Jun-1981 Dec (Box 6)
- Research notebook by Denise Lew, Topoisomerase II (with index), 1982 Jan-Jul (Box 6)
- Binder of research notes, II, pp. 156-161 and unnumbered pages (no index), 1977 Jan-1978 Jun (Box 6)
- Research notebook by Denise Lew, Satellite DNA (with index), 1979 Jul-1980 May (Box 7)
- Research notebook, Satellite sequences, mostly computer printouts (no index) (Box 7)
- Research notebook, Sequence Analysis I, computer printouts (no index) (Box 7)
- Research notebook, Sequence Analysis II, computer printouts (no index) (Box 7)
  Also includes "Nucleic Acid Computer Program Explanatory Manual" by Lawrence Jay Korn, Cary L. Queen, and Mark N. Wegman.
- Research notebook, Bruce Moseley, Satellite DNA Isolation (with index), 1975 Jul-Sep (Box 8)
- Research notebooks, Bruce Moseley, Satellite Isolation and Chromatin Studies, 1976 summer; In Situ hybridization (with index), 1977 summer (Box 8)
- Research notebook, In Situ (with index), 1979 Jan-1980 May (Box 8)
- Research notebook, In Situ (with index), 1977 Nov-1978 Dec (Box 8)
- Research notebook, Nick Translation, DNA on filter, Filter hybrid (no index), 1978-1979 (Box 8)
- Research notebook, unlabeled pp. 2078-2145 (no index) with copy of index for pp. 1-1902 (Box 8)
- Research (notes and computer printouts, no index) (Box 8)
- Notebook, Physical Properties (reference lists, not research notes, no index) (Box 8)
- Notebook, California Institute of Technology, Biophysics of Macromolecules (Bi/Ch 132a) - lab notes (includes class problem sets) (Box 8)
- Notebook, Methods (two copies) - directions for DNA work (Box 8)
- Class materials, binder for S.U. School of Medicine, Biochemistry 101, Autumn 1968, and Biochemistry 102, Winter 1968/69 - notes, lecture outlines (Box 9)
- Class materials, binder for California Institute of Technology, Division of Biology, Bi107, Autumn 1966, Bi107b, Winter 1967, Bi107c, Spring 1967, Bi110, Winter 1968 - notes, etc. (Box 9)
- Class materials, notebook for seminars - papers, etc., 1979-1980 (Box 9)
- EMBL/NIH Workshop "Future Databases for Molecular Biology" at EMBL, Heidelberg February 1987 - conference materials, papers, notes (Box 9)
- CLUSTAL, 1988-1989 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Product Review Board (PRB), 1987-1990 (Box 10, Folder 2)
- National Library of Medicine (NLM) - Law, 1987-1993 (Box 10, Folder 3)
- StrateGene, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- SpeedReader, 1989-1990 (Box 10, Folder 5)
- PEPPER (1), 1987-1988 (Box 10, Folder 6)
- PEPPER (2), 1986-1988 (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Multisequence Alignment Project, 1986-1987 (Box 10, Folder 8)
- BLAZE User Manual, 1992 (Box 11, Folder 1)
- BLAZE, 1991-1995 (Box 11, Folder 2)
- BLAZE-MPsrch Folder, 1993-1994 (Box 11, Folder 3)
- MPsrch, 1990-1993 (Box 11, Folder 4)
- BLAZE-MasPar, 1992-1993 (Box 11, Folder 5)
- DAP (Distributed Array of Processors), 1988-1992 (Box 12, Folder 1)
- Merge 2.0 - Merge II Description (Box 12, Folder 2)
- Database Searcher, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 3)
- Amoco Research Proposal, 1990-1992 (Box 12, Folder 4)
- FastDB, 1988-1991 (Box 12, Folder 5)
- FastDB Paper (Box 12, Folder 6)
- IntelliGenetics Suite (IG Suite), 1987-1992 (Box 12, Folder 7)
- ReQuest, 1988-1992 (Box 13, Folder 1)
- IntelliGenetics, Inc., 1981-1991 (Box 13, Folder 2)
- Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC) / Stock Documents, 1983-1984 (Box 13, Folder 3)
- GenBank, 1987-1994 (Box 13, Folder 4)
- DataGene Proposal, 1986-1988 (Box 13, Folder 5)
- PC/Gene, 1989-1992 (Box 13, Folder 6)
- Redbook, 1988-1990 (Box 14, Folder 1)
- Search/Test results on various databases, MPsrch, 1994 (Box 14, Folder 23)
- Mercury, 1992-1993 (Box 14, Folder 4)
- D. Naor and D. Brutlag manuscript, "On Near-Optimal Alignments of Biological Sequences" (two copies), 1994 Jul (Box 14, Folder 5)
- Genetics Computer Group (GCG), 1987-1988 (Box 14, Folder 6)
- BIONET (1), 1983-1987 (Box 15, Folder 1)
- BIONET (2), 1987-1992 (Box 15, Folder 2)
- BIONET (3), 1997-1988 (Box 15, Folder 3)
- BIONET (4), 1984-1988 (Box 15, Folder 4)
- BIONET Meetings, 1984-1989 (Box 15, Folder 5)
- BIONET Training Manual, TOPS-20 Version 4.0, 1984 (Box 16)
- Binder with BIONET slides (Box 16)
- IntelliGenetics binder with slides (Box 16)
- Automap, 1988 (Box 17, Folder 1)
- ARIAS, 1985-1991 (Box 17, Folder 2)
- SEQ, 1981-1982 (Box 17, Folder 3)
- ASAP (Automatic Sequence Assembly Program), 1988-1992 (Box 17, Folder 4)
- U.S.P.T.O (U.S. Patent and Trademark Office), 1993 (Box 17, Folder 5)
- Miscellaneous Documents, 1982-1987 (Box 17, Folder 6)
- Miscellaneous notes (Box 17, Folder 7)
- FDF - TRW, 1985-1987 (Box 18, Folder 1)
- IntelliCorp, 1983-1989 (Box 18, Folder 2)
- Graphics Spec, 1982 (Box 18, Folder 3)
- National Library of Medicine (NLM) / NIH, 1986-1999 (Box 18, Folder 4)
- Folder of miscellaneous records, 1978-1989 (Box 19)
  Includes faculty minutes and Biochemistry System Proposal by Tito E. Gervacio.
- Monthly financial reports, 1970s-1999 (Box 19)
- Miscellaneous files on products and X/Gene software (Box 19)
- 1 jaz disk labeled "Intelligenetics" (Box 19)
- Copy of Brutlag's Stanford University dissertation: "Enzymatic mechanisms in DNA replication", 1972 (Box 19)